Guide to the Administrative Papers of the Chancellor Henry Mitchell MacCracken 1884-1910 RG.3.0.3
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Chancellor (Henry MacCracken)
1884-1910
New York University Archives
New York University. Office of the Chancellor
RG.3.0.3
12.5 Linear Feet
The Records of the Henry M. MacCracken Administration have been divided into nine series containing materials that pertain to MacCracken's activities as vice chancellor and chancellor of New York University.
Arrangement
All nine series are arranged topically.
This collection has been organized into nine series.
Series
Academic Administration
Finances
Physical Plant
Student Affairs and Activities
Governance
External Relations
Public Relations
Alumni Affairs and Activities
Honorary Degrees
Separated Material
Maps, blueprints and diagrams have been removed from the collection and stored in map cases. For more information on various buildings of the University Heights campus, consult the Buildings Collection in the New York University Archives.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Related information concerning Henry Mitchell MacCracken located within the New York University Archives can be found in the Biographical Files and in the Portrait Files of the University Archives.
The Henry Mitchell MacCracken Papers are also held by the University Archives. This collection is in offsite storage, so you will need to contact the Archives for access.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence, reports, minutes, financial records, printed material, architectural plans and drawings, newspaper clippings, photographs, and notebooks pertaining to MacCracken's activities as Vice Chancellor and Chancellor of New York University from 1884-1910.
Biography
The advent of Henry Mitchell MacCracken as sixth chancellor marked a turning point in the history of New York University. MacCracken had been ordained as a Presbyterian minister, but he already had cast his lot with higher education. In the late 1860s he had spent a year of study in Germany where he became acquainted with German practice in the development of graduate study. Based upon this experience he would eventually stress the importance of adding postgraduate work to the curriculum in the arts and sciences at New York University.
Since 1880 he had been Chancellor of the Western University of Pennsylvania (now the University of Pittsburgh). MacCracken came to New York University as Professor of Philosophy, but in June 1885, he was appointed Vice Chancellor. The circumstances of his appointment made it clear that the Council of New York University and especially the acting Chancellor, the Reverend John Hall, were grooming the newcomer for the Chancellorship, which he assumed in 1891.
As Chancellor of New York University from 1891 until 1910, MacCracken oversaw the purchase of the University Heights Campus and the construction of the present-day Main Building at Washington Square. He was also responsible for the reorganization of the Law School and the Medical School and the establishment of the Graduate School, the School of Pedagogy, the College of Engineering, the School of Commerce, and the Collegiate Division. In being both clergyman and educator, MacCracken symbolized the transition of the University from a small educational operation to one that in scope, organization, and administration laid the basis of the twentieth-century University.
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers.
Provenance
The administrative records of Henry Mitchell MacCracken were transferred from the Chancellor's office of New York University to Gould Memorial Library on the University Heights campus following the retirement of MacCracken in 1910. The records, including personal papers of MacCracken, were added to the New York University Historical Collection, which was housed in the Treasurer Room of the library. With the closing of the Heights campus in 1973, the Historical Collection was transferred to the Washington Square campus of the University, where it formed the nucleus of the University Archives.
Greek letter societies.; College administrators -- Selection and appointment; Dissertations.; Public relations.; Universities and Colleges -- Administration; Scholarships.; Notebooks; Budgets.; photoprints.; Universities and Colleges -- Professional education.; Universities and Colleges -- Finance; Bylaws (administrative records); Architectural drawings (visual works); Universities and Colleges -- Curricula.; National Conference on Foreign Policy (Saratoga, N.Y.); University of the City of New York; American Veterinary College; American Book Company; Alumni Federation of New York University, Inc; New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science; Bouton, Archibald Lewis, 1872-1941; Gould, Helen Miller; Gould, Jay, 1836-1892; General Education Board (New York, N.Y.); Gould, Frank Jay; McKim, Mead & White; Draper, Anna P.; Eliot, Charles William, 1834-1926; Chautauqua Educational System; Columbia University; Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919; Biggs, Hermann M. (Hermann Michael), 1859-1923; Bellevue Hospital; New York University. Graduate School of Arts and Science; Ashley, Clarence D. (Clarence Degrand), 1851-1916; Balliet, Thomas M. (Thomas Minard), 1852-1942; Association of American Universities; New York University. Hall of Fame for Great Americans; Harvard University; Haskins & Sells; Haskins, Charles W.; Hudson-Fulton Celebration Commission; Louisiana Purchase Exposition. (1904: Saint Louis, Mo.); Macdougall, Robert; New York Columbian Celebration; New York Hemopathic College; MacCracken, Henry Mitchell, 1840-1918; New York University. College of Engineering; New York University. Carnegie Laboratory; New York University. Council; New York University. College of Medicine; New York University -- Presidents; New York University. Loomis Laboratory; New York University -- Endowments; New York University. School of Education; New York University. School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance; New York University. Finance Office; New York University. School of Applied Science; New York University. School of Engineering and Science; New York University. Summer School; New York University. School of Medicine; New York University. Trustees; North American Veterinary College; Ohio Society of New York; New York University. Women's Advisory Committee; Peabody, Francis; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison), 1839-1937; Pan-American Exposition (1901: Buffalo, NY); Paris. Exposition; Sihler, E. G. (Ernest Gottlieb), 1853-1942; Snow, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1863-1957; Schiff, Jacob H. (Jacob Henry), 1847-1920; Shaw, Edward R.; Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.); Stokes, James; Strong, Josiah, 1847-1916; Zucker, Alfred, 1852-; New York University. Washington Square College of Arts and Science; White, Stanford, 1853-1906; Weir, Samuel
- Series I: Academic Administration
  Scope and Contents note
  The records relate to the Vice Chancellor's and Chancellor's office, the University College of Arts and Pure Science, the University's professional schools (Graduate, Law, Engineering, Medical, Veterinary, Commerce, and Pedagogy), the Women's Advisory Committee of the School of Pedagogy, and special programs and facilities.
  The Vice Chancellor's and Chancellor's files include correspondence describing MacCracken's selection of vice chancellor and the proposed selection of his son John H. MacCracken as his successor, miscellaneous correspondence, and annual reports. There is very limited documentation concerning the activities of John MacCracken as syndic or acting chancellor of New York University.
  The University College material includes information about the classics, English and geology departments, and the chemical and physical laboratories. These files contain correspondence from faculty members, including Ernest G. Sihler, professor of Classics, Archibald Bouton, professor of English and later dean of University College, Morris Loeb of the chemical laboratory, and Daniel W. Hering, professor of Physics. The classics department file also includes two articles by Sihler. The geology department file describes the search for a successor to John J. Stevenson. Examination questions pertain to various departments. Material in all folders is arranged in chronological order.
  The professional schools files contain material about the Graduate School (Graduate Seminary), Law School, School of Applied Science (Engineering), University Medical College (University and Bellevue Medical College), the New York American Veterinary College, the School of Commerce, Accounts and Finance, and the School of Pedagogy. Correspondence, reports and printed material comprises the documents found for most schools. In 1899, the chemical and physical laboratories became part of the School of Applied Science. Material for the two laboratories before and after 1899, however, is found in the University College folders of the collection. Letters from applicants for faculty positions in the School of Pedagogy are arranged in alphabetical order; material in all other folders is arranged chronologically.
  The Graduate School (Graduate Seminary) records consist of correspondence and reports, some of which are from John D. Prince, dean of the school, 1895-1902. Theological studies material includes an 1890 agreement between N.Y.U. and the Union Theological Seminary.
  The Law School files include correspondence from Austin Abbott and Clarence D. Ashley, deans of the schools, 1891-1896 and 1896-1916 respectively. There is limited information about the Women's Law Class and no material on the Metropolis Law School. (For information on these subjects, see Records of the Women's Law Class and the Womens Legal Aid Society, and Records of the Metropolis Law School, in the New York University Archives).
  The School of Applied Sciences (Engineering) records include correspondence and reports from Charles H. Snow, dean of the school, 1899-1930, dating from as early as 1892.
  The University Medical College files contain information about the merger between the University Medical College and the Bellevue Hospital Medical College in 1898, the subsequent Loomis Laboratory lawsuit, and the proposed affiliation with the New York Homeopathic College. Correspondence from Egbert LeFevre, dean of the school, 1898-1914, and Herman M. Biggs; financial records and printed material also are included in these files. The financial records describe the physical facilities of the school and include correspondence with Andrew Carnegie about the Carnegie Laboratory.
  The New York American Veterinary College files contain correspondence about the establishment of the school, legislation affecting the college's operation, reports, lists of students, and printed material.
  The School of Commerce, Accounts and Finance records consist of correspondence of Charles W. Haskins, first dean of the school 1900-1903, and partner in the accounting firm of Haskins and Sells. Many of the documents, including faculty correspondence, financial information, course descriptions, printed material, and newspaper clippings, pertain to the establishment of the school.
  The School of Pedagogy material provides information about the 1901 controversy over admissions standards which led to mass faculty resignations. In addition, some documents describe MacCracken's role as acting dean from 1901 to 1904. There is virtually no information about the Summer School.
  The Women's Advisory Committee material relates primarily to the operation of the School of Pedagogy, including information about the 1901 controversy, faculty appointments, courses, and finances. Minute books covering the period 1890 to 1911 provide much information about the committee's activities.
  Special programs/facilities includes information about the Deems lectures, the Bermuda biological station, various N.Y.U. libraries, and limited material concerning the Hall of Fame.
  - Vice Chancellor's Office
    - Correspondence re Appointment at New York University, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Annual Report, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chancellor's Office
    - Correspondence, 1892-1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Art History (Wallace Wood), 1895-1909 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Astronomy (Edward S. Holder), 1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - MacCracken, John H.: possible selection as successor, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Annual Reports, including Synod's Committee on Visitation, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Annual Report for 1894, 1895, Jan. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Annual Report for 1897-1898 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Annual Report, 1902, Nov. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Annual Report, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - University College
    - Faculty Committees: Curricular matters, 1898-1909 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Classics department, 1894, 1901-1904 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - English department, 1888, 1904-1909 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Geology department, 1899-1909 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Physics laboratory, 1888, 1893, 1906-1908, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Chemistry department and laboratory, 1893-1909, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Other departments, 1892-1895, 1900, 1904-1907 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Examination questions (misc. fields), 1886-1888 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Examination questions (misc. fields), 1889-1906, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Dedication of University Heights Campus, letters re, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Summer School
    - Summer School, 1899-1907 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Graduate School
    - Correspondence and papers, 1893-1905, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Theological studies, 1890-1910 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Law School
    - Correspondence, 1890-1902 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Advertising, 1891-1892 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Women's Law Class, 1892, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Printed material, 1867, 1900, 1905-1909 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - School of Applied Science (Engineering)
    - Correspondence, 1892-1910, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Reports, 1895-1909, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - University Medical College
    - Correspondence and documents, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Faculty appointments, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Faculty appointments, 1898, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and documents, 1883-1899 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and documents, 1900-1904 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Statements by MacCracken, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Statements and resolutions by the University Council, 1897-1898 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - New York Homeopathic College, affiliation with, 1904-1905 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Egbert LeFevre, 1897-1908 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Herman M. Biggs, 1899-1904 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Student Correspondence, 1901-1910 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Budgets and expense reports, 1891-1908 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - New Building, 1897-1904, Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Carnegie Laboratory: Andrew Carnegie, 1899-1909, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Bills, 1899-1900 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and reports, 1883, 1897-1908 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Controversy, printed material re, 1898 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Faculty changes, MacCracken's notes re, 1898? (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - New York American Veterinary College
    - Correspondence, 1899-1908, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Legislation and related correspondence, 1894, 1904-1910 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Reports, ca. 1910 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Student lists, ca. 1900 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Printed material, 1897-1909, Undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - School of Commerce, Accounts and Finance
    - Charles Waldo Haskins, 1899-1900 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Charles Waldo Haskins, 1900-1902 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Faculty acceptances, 1900 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Unsuccessful faculty applicants, 1900-1901 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - General, 1900-1908, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1900, 1905-1909 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Finances, 1901, 1905-1906 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Courses, 1899-1901, Undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Haskins and Sells/Haskins, 1897, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Commercial education (flyers), 1899-1901 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1899-1900 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - School of Pedagogy
    - Antecedents, 1889 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Foundng, 1890 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Courses and Faculty, 1900-1904 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Faculty controversy, 1901 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Administrative matters, 1891, 1898-1907 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Protests re resignation of faculty, 1901 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Board of Education, 1901-1902 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Proposed pedagogical journal, 1901 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Proposed kindergarten, 1902-1903 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Proposed pedagogical library, 1902 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Proposed children's school/farm, 1907 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Edward R. Shaw (dean, 1894-1901), 1900-1901 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Edward F. Buckner, 1900-1901 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Samuel Weir, 1900-1903 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - F. Montser, 1901-1902 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Charles H. Judd, 1901-1902 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - L. E. LaFetra, 1901 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - J. P. Gordy, 1901 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Robert MacDougall, 1901 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Thomas M. Balliet: Appointment, 1904 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Thomas M. Balliet: Correspondence, 1904-1919 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Lecturers, 1901-1904 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Applicants and appointees, A-K, 1901-1909 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Applicants and appointees, M-W, 1901-1909 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1900-1906, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Petitions, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Lists, 1894-1905 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Finances, 1901-1906 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Printed Material, 1889-1902, Undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Women's Advisory Committee
    - Historical notes on, and excerpts from, minutes of University Council, 1890 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - By-Laws, Annual Reports, 1890-1903 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - General, 1893, 1896-1904 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Katherine Bacon Smith, 1893, 1897-1904 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Emily O. Butler, 1900-1901 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Anna P. Draper, 1900-1901 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Discussion of conditions of School of Pedagogy, 1901 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Financial reports, 1901-1910 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Printed Material, ca. 1890, Undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - "Invitation List," address book, 1891 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Ledger (expenditures and donations), 1898-1901 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Minute book, 1890-1899 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Minute book, 1899-1911 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Library
    - Manuscript account of origins, ca. 1909 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, bills, regulations, 1899-1908 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - La Garde Library and purchase of R. Huebner Library, 1901-1902 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - American Institute of Christian Philosophy
    - Papers re agreement between Institute and New York University; establishment of Deems Lectureship, 1894-1895 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence re membership and membership lists, 1892-1897 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, 1895-1908 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Activities in connection with Chautauqua System of Education: Correspondence with George F. Vincent, Josiah Strong, George D. Boardman, Francis G. Peabody, 1895 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Arthur James Balfour; correspondence, 1905 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Financial reports, 1889-1905 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Administrative correspondence, 1895-1906 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Printed Material, 1894-1895 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - University Biological Laboratory at Bermuda
    - University Biological Laboratory at Bermuda (Joint venture with Harvard University): Correspondence with Charles W. Eliot and C. L. Bristol, 1901-1906 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Hall of Fame for Great Americans
    - Hall of Fame for Great Americans, 1900-1905, Undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Series II: Finances
  Records concerning University finances consist of registrar's reports, fiscal statements, department budgets, faculty pensions, and student tuition costs, dormitory rentals and scholarships. Income from gifts and grants indicate the contributions and endowments made during the period, including support from the General Education Board, a Rockefeller-sponsored institution. The Gould family records contain extensive correspondence with Helen Miller Gould, daughter of Jay Gould, concerning scholarships, contributions, and construction at University Heights, made possible through the generous benefaction of the Gould family.
  - University Finances
    - University Finances, ca. 1892-1893 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Registrar's Reports, 1898-1900 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Fiscal Statements, 1891-1908 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - College and department expenditures, including salaries, 1892-1910 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence with Bursar, Frank A. Fall, 1907-1910 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Faculty pensions; Carnegie Foundation for Advancement of Teaching, 1905-1910 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Students
    - Tuition (loans and fees), 1893-1910 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Dormitory rentals, admission and scholarships, 1896, 1901, Undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1897-1910 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - John Hall Memorial Scholarship, 1898-1899 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Ottendorfer Memorial Scholarship, 1900 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Geneva Printing Company Scholarship, 1904 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Gifts and Grants
    - Printed appeals, 1889-1895 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Printed Appeals, 1893 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Russell Sage, 1898 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Jacob Schiff, 1898 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - John D. Rockefeller (General Education Board), 1898-1907 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - General, 1901, 1902 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Andrew H. Green, heirs of, 1903 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Subscription Drive; miscellaneous correspondence; lists; Lyman Abbott, 1904 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - James Stokes, 1904 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1906-1908 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Description of University for promotional purposes; educational side; business side, Undated (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Proposed Foundation for American Education, Undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Endowments and Trusts
    - Endowed professorships, trust funds for special objects; Consolidated Endowment Fund; Sandham Gift, 1896-1907 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Jay Gould, 1892-1893 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Frank Jay Gould, 1896-1899 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Helen Miller Gould, 1892-1897 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Helen Miller Gould, 1898-1899 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Helen Miller Gould, 1900-1903 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Helen Miller Gould, 1904-1905, 1907/1909 Undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Gould Scholarships, 1899 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Gould Scholarships, 1902-1904 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Financial statements re gifts of Helen Gould, 1900-1904 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous bills, 1891-1895, 1900-1901 (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Series III: Physical Plant
  University properties at Washington Square and University Heights are the principal concerns in the files on physical plant. Washington Square material relates to the construction, furnishing, and rental of Main Building, which was designed by the architect, Alfred Zucker and constructed in 1894. The files include extensive material documenting the lease agreements on the building between the University and the American Book Company.
  Records concerning the University Heights property are divided into three categories: real estate, building and construction, and furnishing and rental.